[Music]
welcome again everybody this is yasir
wazife from learn dental series we will
continue to this our discussion about
the topic of diagnosis and treatment
planning and operative dentistry
i declare that i don't receive face
compensation or realities from the sales
of any of the products shown or
discussed also this presentation has not
been sponsored by any company agency or
organization
and is prepared only for educational
purposes i also remind you about the
copyright of this presentation which is
copyright protected and could not be
transmitted by any
mean unless you get
a braille permission of those
in this episode we will continue
our discussion and we will today
correlate between the oral and dental
clinical findings and superposed
treatment plan
and we will focus and properly diagnose
dental care by different techniques in
the previous episode we already started
to discuss part one including patient
assessment and the information gathering
in terms of demographic demographic data
chief complaint and ancestry medical
history and the telestream today we will
continue
forward to discuss the clinical
examination and diagnosis especially
we will start with diagnosis of dental
caries first of all we will
differentiate between the terminology of
examination and diagnosis examination is
a process while diagnosis is the result
okay
or the nomination of your examination of
the result of your
examination like that we are examining
all the students in any class okay
regardless he is one of the top or
one of the five bottom students all
students should be examined regardless
their level of intelligence regardless
their iq they are all should be examined
but the leveling of the result this one
get a plus mark this one get a grade b
grade like this this is diagnosis the
result of the exam that's why the
process of observing and testing both
normal and abnormal conditions
regarding regardless the complaint is
called
examination diagnosis is a determination
and judgment of variations from normal
giving the name to the abnormality we
observed or we examined or the result of
the test is called diagnosis this is the
difference then
what we are going to do is examination
okay followed by the result will be the
diagnosis that's why it's examination
procedure related to or resulting in a
diagnosis okay we will start with our
major interest which is examination of
dental cares
examination of dental care is as said by
socrat before
to find an accurate method for detecting
and diagnosis any disease
is the goal of healing art okay
because if you don't diagnose the
condition
okay you will not
perfectly design a treatment plan to fix
it that's why
terrorist diagnosis is not just to
detect it
cares diagnosis okay it is an
interesting place on the way
to
for treatment decision
you couldn't get your treatment decision
or treatment plan without accurate and
perfect diagnosis of dental caries
and dental caries is not
diagnosis is not the detection of its
presence only is it present or not it is
seen or not it is an intellectual
process in determining the present and
the extent and the activity of the
legion all these are integral part of
their losing dental care cares as well
as not only assessment of the activity
of the legion but also all the
circumstances the environments the
conditions related to
developing the scariest lesion
okay
because activity
of the lesion okay
requires either
active or inactive management okay
active management could be operative or
non-operative management treatment okay
while the arrested lesion
in active lesion okay needs another plan
that's why early diagnosis of terrorist
lesion is important because carious
process can be modified as early as you
discovered it and could be reversed
without any traumatic management
or
cutting the cavity your manager of the
management of dental caries could be
as simple as modifying the oral hygiene
habits of the patient and just adding
fluoride application in a way or another
and could be severely traumatized as
indirect restoration or may go for
endurance both score and problem okay
that's why as said by socrat a goal
without a plan is just a wish
you should plan
to achieve your goal
let me give you an example okay all of
these four cases are diagnosed
as pets and facial cares
okay
if you think by the same classical
routine
management
designed
more than
120 years by giving black okay then you
will cut and debris bear
a classical or routine class one
including old bits and fishes okay for
all of these classes
while actually or recent practice
density okay
and all the recent literature okay and
all the recent techniques okay we'll
show you a different management although
they are all classified and diagnosed as
symbol closure class one
but number one
are they all
as simple as you
read the word
symbol
okay
are they
all the same simplistic as you say
symbol
you say symbol because it is one service
but you didn't consider the management
of the world you haven't any idea about
what is inside the two and at those
underneath this discoloration
that's why okay if you try to manage
these four cases you will discover that
number one is just a little bit
discoloration of a deep fissure
okay that needs only itching of the
surface and the blazing bits and fissure
sealant as simple as that okay either
from the right containing or not okay
or
it is
with
application of fluoride either topical
in a professional way or a topical using
mouse washes or mouse rinses whatever
you are
you will do okay but it is
still at dramatic management you didn't
go for operation you needed to go for
cutting tooth structure okay the other
one
shows that you just have a little bit
penetration extension of your cares into
enamel
okay
just
just touching the
junction but not all the two surfaces if
you prefer it as a classical or routine
class one that of blacks cavities okay
it will be a massive damage you could
imagine the heroes is only limited to
this whole and you will go for
distracting
the remaining occlusal surface okay and
you will go just only for preventive
resin menstruation
just
sealing this cavity
this minimal invasive cavity with
suitable restorative material okay and
accompanies this with bits and fisher
sealant for the other
while
the third one
which looks
from the occlusal point of view just a
visual examination it looks like just
a little bit
extension more than the second one but
when we open this we discovered the
steps
and to how extent
your buccal cusps are undermined and
that's why you are applying a flexible
base material okay and you are designing
the preparation for to receive bonded
restoration in a form of direct
composite resin restoration just to
reinforce the weakened
buckle cusps and crosstalk them with
strong palatal cusps okay and this is
the maximum conservative approach in
such a case while another one
which
seems like the third one okay but when
we open this we discover
a wider buckle extension to the other
side and it doesn't become simple as we
could imagine remember that the top four
pictures are torment or diagnosed and
symbol
okay
the third one is not symbol biologically
or mechanically because already we have
undermined buccal clasps and we already
should evaluate the activity of the
hairs okay
if we apply the concept of g black then
the third one you should remove all of
these discoloration and the all of these
discretion discoloration and the case
will be referred to and longest okay the
same for this one last one okay it is
diagnosed as symbol occlusal class one
but actually when we go to remove the
carries okay we discovered a wide mesial
distal buccal extension
and the gravity becomes compound not
symbol
okay then the simple term that describes
the number of involving surface and
involved services and securities
procedures it is of no value in
treatment planning
it is not describing how much is the
case the case is simple or difficult it
just counts the number of surfaces
when we
as you could notice here okay the
operator trying to diagnose the
occlusion okay and he find a massive
occlusal center coding areas that's why
may he may go for indirect aesthetic
restoration
okay
and this is the final fate of your case
then
you have
two cases to the left and the two cases
rulers to the right
all are diagnosed routinely by the older
concept as symbol occlusal class one
while the management is not as simple as
that okay we have the two to the right
okay are
just early careers lesion with minimal
minimal
dramatic cutting of the two structure
while the others okay other two to the
right two pictures or two cases to the
right are extensively damaged
one
is not as simple as we termed it okay
because of mechanically already
zacchaeus undermines the buccal cusps
and biologically cares extended deep
okay into the pulp
you should
get a proper idea about the extension
and a proper idea about the activity of
your curious lesion okay also the last
one we discovered it is not even simple
okay
as it includes more than one service
okay that's why we are in need
to get
a diagnostic tool that could diagnose
cares in the early stage of the two
cases to the left rather than the two
cases to the right because we would like
to manage cares okay as simple
as it is early detected because it is
the least
aggressive one
if you consider failure of restoration
okay
the cases to the left as early as i
detect dental cares still have a chance
and another and another and another and
another until rich reach to indirect
frustration i could repeat the
restoration many times i still have a
chance to get less aggressive treatment
while those to the right okay
i don't have
these chances i will go either for full
coverage or i will go to sacrifice upon
okay
and after that comes extraction okay and
maybe
fixed prosthodontics or going for emblem
supported brusson index
okay
it go forward aggressively and firstly
to more aggressive treatment
okay while
the cases to the left we like it because
still i have too much chances to repeat
our registration
that is why
gerry's detection method should be
capable of detecting
lesions at early stages as possible
when progression can be reversed or
arrested
that's why we will avoid premature
tooth treatment by restoration
okay
at this stage you are saving tooth
structure you are saving time saving
money
saving stress for you and your patient
also considering the infection control
in general
the visit will be for few minutes
not for few hours
okay and increasing the time of visit
nowadays within the endemic of covet 19
and a much
spread
infectious disease you need to
listen the time required for your
treatment and made it as simple as
possible and as successful as possible
you should also ensure a good perfect
prognosis for your case
that's why we shouldn't differentiate
between
two terminologies we should
differentiate between detection and
diagnosis okay detections means that the
determination
of the presence
and the extent of carious lesion
including its activity that's it but it
is not that simple as a diagnosis not
only determining the presence of dental
cares and extent
of its activity but also we should
the risk factors including patient
attitude and behavior because all of
these
plays an important role in the success
of minimal invasives at invasive and
dramatic preparations okay because
proper diagnosis proper early diagnosis
constitutes a cornerstone of treatment
planning and success and prevention of
recurrence
that's
why we can't treat what we can see
so you should inspect and see the
problem
by a way or another from all aspects and
from all dimensions
that's why the proper careers management
plan
could be assigned only if you could see
your gears in 3d in three dimensions
what is meant by three dimensions the
first dimension is early detection
okay
then the second is the contributing and
risk factors which affecting its third
dimension which is activity that's why
when you would like to pre design a
preventive program or when you would
like to reverse this activity of
demineralization of dental caries you
should see your carers from three
dimensions okay
that's why let us start with the old
concept
in diagnosing dental care and how we
could modify it or how it was modified
already for detection of early caries
lesion and determining all the condition
and circumstances related to its
extension and its presence and its
activity okay starting with traditional
techniques okay then going for advanced
theories and detection aids in cares as
risk assessment let's start with
traditional techniques and the simplest
one is to see which is the visual
examination
visual examination
is a widely used and the simplest
diagnostic technique or examination
technique to be definite let's say
examination okay
it relies on
with seeing a curious lesion that's a
symbol okay but you should have a sharp
eyes for sharp side or definite accurate
side that's why it is recommended to use
magnification simply from the loops it
is now available in old lender marks
okay and easy to get one okay with
different magnifications okay and we
need a good illumination either from the
overhead dental chair light or some
dental loops having a headlight
especially lid one coupled with it okay
and it provides a great accessibility to
see the surface then the surface should
be clean and dry okay
because sometimes
we may
misdiagnose dental caries and could not
differentiate between dental cares and
the remnants of food or
any discoloration that's why you should
use the triple way sea ridge
okay to clean your surface from any
difference
sometimes the tools may be covered by
black or calculus and that's why your
for proper diagnosis your patient should
be
or should be referred for hygienist or
main meds
before making you or meeting any of the
other practitioners okay just to exclude
that there is a debris or black or
calculus that may hide a lesion or may
hide a dental cares okay number four
nowadays we didn't use sharp explorer
okay we use
round
or bowl ended what is called whoa dental
probe because sharp explorer
may may
indicate the formation of cavitation
and may lead to breakdown of
fragile enamel okay inducing further
cavitation okay and at the same time
we'll commence this how you would make
sure that the attack back action you
felt by the explorer is not due to
friction between the walls of the fisher
anatomical fissure and
the size of the explorer and when you
are forcing it already you are reducing
micro fracture of your enamels there is
too much questions and too much remarks
about using this this is why nowadays we
recommend the use as is the use of pull
and the dental probes of wh o okay
sometimes for proximal lesions you are
need to use to separation especially to
see visually if you don't have a
radiograph or any other mean to inspect
visually the interproximal incident
carries in such a condition we may use
oversized wooden wedge
okay for a
few minutes and sometimes we are
using orthodontic elastic separators for
maximum three days okay just to displace
the changeable tissues and to provide a
little bit separation between these two
to see or inspect the proximal surface
finally you should have sufficient time
to examine all the tooth surfaces
examine your tooth from all five
surfaces the two proximal sparkle and
lingual and occlusal or incisor okay it
is not as simple as you expect by naked
eye the surface it's okay it's free from
uh discoloration then it is sound no you
should inspect have your time to inspect
the truth and examine it visually from
all sides including soft tissue and
proton
this is an example of
magnification loops with
higher magnification to the right side
this magnification loop is accompanied
by a lid
okay sometimes some operators prefer it
with light overhead light and i'm one uh
this overhead light is annoying to me
okay i am not accustomed to use it i i
need uh
much more training to use it okay
this is an active carious lesion
but we couldn't definitely
define
what is the extent of the lesion what is
the activity of the lesion because it is
covered by black that's why comes the
importance of cleaning the surface okay
cleaning the surface as you could see in
figure c
gives you a definite
picture and the mental imaging about the
extent of the curious lesion and its
activity which is not clear
as that
in figure a and b
while it is covered by
dental block okay also
the figure a in such a condition
did not reflect that was scariest or not
is there a demineralization or not
because already it is wet with saliva
you should
dry your surface okay
washing it and drying it with a
triple a syringe and you could after
dryness discover as seen in figure b
okay a white demineralization area
indicating
starting various activity related to
this fissure
finally
this tools has a cervical area showing a
white spot lesion this wide spot lesion
may be a hyper mineralization or high
bone mineralization as you see in figure
b
there is a cone
with
wide discoloration in enamel okay
indicating demineralization okay if you
insert a sharp explorer inside it it is
not up till now cavitated and up to now
if you don't use the explorer
like that in trigger c then it could be
infiltrated with risen it could be even
go for much more simple treatment by
remineralizing agent or fluoride okay
thus just to seal some microbrowsers in
enamel
that indicated
demineralization and leads to this white
opaque
line that's why it is not recommended at
all to use sharp explorer it already
cavitated this fragile enamel leading to
the habitation that needs to be sealed
and needs
application of other artificial material
maybe
gic maybe floral composite and it will
go for much more complicated procedure
than remineralization indicating maybe
cutting the cavity indicating there may
be a
ponding procedure with its technique
sensitivities that's why it is not
recommended this is a simple example why
we are not recommended now using this
sharp explorer another view showing the
orthodontic elastic separators
that will allow applied
for few minutes if you are
if it gets
a result or maximum okay for three days
okay to inspect to drive your gingival
tissues away
and give you enough space which is
temporarily created and the tools will
again repositioned because you are
within the elastic limits of your
periodontal fibers don't use too much
separation or it will be permanent
separation it's a temporary simulation
okay just enables you to just inspect by
your eye either under manufacture or not
what is hidden in the interproximal area
this is a visual examination the
principles of visual examination depends
upon
the changes of the tooth
structure
okay
mainly affected by
the idea of how the keris gets inside
enamel
okay
keris
leads to asset solubility of enamel okay
in interrupt substance more than rods
then there will be a microporosity on if
enamel due to demineralization
this will in turn affect
light reflection of enamel and gives you
the chalky white okay of the enamel or
the color changes of the enamel
after that these microbores
could attract stains from food debris
and that's why it gets darker
discoloration then it all starts by
microprocessors due to demineralization
of enamel okay
this will
alter the light transmission and the
reflection through enamel and gives you
a chalky white appearance okay
this microbulls could be
sealed or occupied by stains okay until
a full demineralization and the enamel
is destructed creating cavities okay
these are the stages
of
what you could see visually see during
enamel okay uh curious uh cares progress
that's why
you could notice either cavitation in
advanced lesions or
you could detect color it changes
but
all of these means is that already
enamel is damaged
and sometimes
demineralization could not be notes
either by the patient or either by you
you are depending on how lucky you are
and how your patient is keen to inspect
his teeth to that extent he could not
just choke the right appearance which is
actually
untrue
okay
that's why
the decision of absence of prison of
allegiance is based on subjective
interpretation of the integrity
texture
translucency obasi location and the
color okay
finally this concluded that visual
examination reveals dental care is by
either discoloration or cavitation
okay
let us discuss these cases
in brief case number one showing
carry spits on the fissure on cusp tip
it's a visual cavitation
case number b loss of translucency and
the change in color as already enamel is
going far in demineralization and the
micro browsers are occupied by stains
from food and drinks
okay vincum case
comes case c would show
turkey white beer and or a shadow under
the marginal ridge it's not only a choki
white but also accompanied in the center
with brown discoloration another one is
case d
in cb and smooth surface carries lesion
okay or a wise spot
in certain cases okay showing
a inductor vis pass already you have
obvious discoloration
the same as
case e it accompanies smooth surface
carries appears white or dark depending
on the degree of extrinsic stains
penetration
and the worst condition is accompanied
by ginger recession which shows
discoloration and the cavitation with
black accumulation
okay
let us discuss more definitely another
case which is the white spot cervical
lesion okay as we said before this
chalky white area okay that appears
in this cervical
place it may be
misdiagnosed okay with
hyper mineralization or hypo
mineralization and the enamel didn't
have any microprocessors in such a case
we are depending on what is described as
disappearing reappearing phenomena just
imagine that this part of enamel is
demineralized
having
a demineralized spaces microspaces that
are occupied with saliva when they are
occupied with salivary signations of
saliva or water okay
before getting discolored by food
stagnation or extrinsic stains at this
stage as you could see
this lesion okay maybe a lesion or it
may be a normal
hyper or hypo mineralization without
microprocess then
you are in need
definitely to diagnose the presence of
microprocess
not the presence of discoloration
in an
elusive trek
using our knowledge if it is
microboroughs
then
with wetting it will be occupied with
saliva that will hidden this
discoloration okay and after dryness
like that of acid etching you are
removing saliva from this micro
processes and it will appear turkey
white that's why we will use
disappearing reappearing phenomena just
drying it
okay
it appears then asking the patient to
rinse or wet it again with the
triple-way syringe is disappears then
re-dry it appears again then it's
an active demineralization starting at
the cervical lesion or this smooth
surface cavities okay but still it was
not occupied by extrinsic stain to the
extent that it could be visually
diagnosed as mental cares okay if
it resists under wet or dry conditions
the same then it is there is no
microprocessors that affects the
transmission and the reflection of light
okay this is a simple way for wide spot
cervical lesion which is called
disappearing reappearing phenomena that
affects the visual examination of the
presence or absence of careless activity
in general
the visual examination
having
an important limitation it is it is a
subject it is subjectively
or its subjectivity
between different practitioners
especially of early lesion
that's why its reliability and validity
is considered questionable as a
diagnostic tools in early lesions
because
what i could
see it by my necked eye according to the
my vision power or according to my
experience as considered as discolored
okay someone could not see it is this
colored someone could see that this is
the normal color of this patient teeth
okay
that's why okay
it's
reliability
and the validity as examination tool for
the presence of dental cares
is much higher in cavitated rather than
the skeletal lesions
okay
that's why
there is no doubt between operator and
another this is a gravitated lesion and
this is a gravitated lesion but in early
discoloration there is much more debate
but on the much more
uh difference
subject in the subjectivity between
different practitioners
that's why in early lesion it is not
reliable okay and
not accurate not not valid okay
and now
when it comes to cavitation already we
have a disaster
okay we are on the right side
we we we discussed before where we go
for cavity variation and we go for
determining the valve conditions the
degree of enamel uh
destruction and it is direct or indirect
restoration no we are need to be to the
left side we recommend it just pits and
fissure or even bits and fischer is
considered as an aggressive treatment we
need to just modify the patient attitude
okay applying mineralizing agent to
infill infiltrate these microbiologists
stop the care's activity reverse the
condition okay maximumly if we go for
treatment we go for preventive resistant
restoration okay then
should i wait
to that extent
to visually determine a cavitation to
say that this is this juice is curious
or not here comes a recent modifications
okay
for uh
starting from
the new century uh 20 years ago or
lesser i think it's just 15 years what
is called cares detection indices
they are an attempt to correct the
limitation of visual examination okay
introduced by including reliable
criteria for detecting early lesions
okay and for monitoring clinical status
of these early lesions these indices
used epidemiological studies to measure
the prevalence and severity of dental
cares
it's a huge work
using a huge
data okay uh from different
countries from different practitioners
okay this work
already
entails contribution of
a huge number of cardiologists worldwide
okay all of them was iconic cardiologist
and the epidemiologist where they
collect the data of what about the
consensus of
caries
visual examination and the correlated to
the histological pattern or the
histological advancement of curious
lesion okay
that's why these indices
were designed to describe additional
stages of carious process including both
cavitated and the early non-gravitated
lesions
those cares detection and this that will
be discussed in the next episodes
in full details including icdus which is
international abbreviation of
international cares detection and
assessment system
which uses visual surface
characteristics to measure surface
changes and potential osteological
depths that says of curious lesion it's
in general all of these instances are
trying to standardize
and translate what you have seen
okay
to
a number to a score which describes the
condition and sometimes describes
entertainment it's a trial to
standardize
the subjectivity of visual examination
between different practitioners okay
then comes
botha bova is a provision of pulp ulcer
fistula and abscess system okay
this focus on the staging
the most severe levels of keri's disease
okay then comes caste which scares
assessment spectrum and treatment which
includes staging
careers lesion both for oral early and
more for severe level and finally
american dental association cares
classification system which describe
both cavitated and non-cavitated lesions
by clinical presentation without
reference to specific treatment approach
but it links clinical lesion
presentation to radiographic findings
and to provide an approach to identify
when possible curious lesion activity
over a time
this will be discussed in details in the
next coming episodes
those are
the references i used in preparing this
presentation if you are in need for
further reading this is suggested
reading finally
don't hesitate to ask me
feel free to ask at any time as your
questions are always welcome by just
commenting to this video and i will
reply to you as soon as possible or you
could send me i email an email by my
contact info and also i will reply to
you as soon as possible finally thank
you for assigning this time to listen to
me please don't forget to
subscribe to my channel
and like this video and activate the
notification to get all the updates of
this
educational channel thank you again yes
sir no see